Hello?
Can you hear me? I can't hear you.
Can't hear you
now.
Still nothing. Can you hear me?
Hello?
Hello? Hi. Let's we go. How are you?
Good. How are you?
Uh, here. I'm here.
Get a rough weekend or? Uh, yeah.
Um, yeah,
RA rainbow's been having some hard times.
Uh, so they've been officially diagnosed with, uh, anxiety
and a DHD on top of the autism,
Uh, Aa.
Yeah, aaa. Uh, they've been, uh, I mean,
they're very creative and it's very cool,
but they've, they use this like industrial size,
like professional kitchen size thing of like plastic wrap,
uh, to create some fashion.
So they're just like walking around like some kind of,
I don't know, future space w***e, like, it's just,
and they won't take it off.
So it's, and it's, anyway,
Dana put the Photo, it covers it, it covers nothing
that it should co Anyway, it's,
uh, you know, uh, how are you doing?
How was your weekend?
Good. Bunch of soccer.
Oh, nice. I know that, uh, uh,
Arlo is very much looking forward to
it not being f*****g minus.
You are, you're already a cohost, right? Yeah. You are?
Yeah. Okay, good. Mm-hmm.
Uh, I know, uh,
Arlo is very much looking forward it to, for it
to not be minus 30 so that they can play soccer again.
Is it still minus 30 now?
Yeah, it has like, wow.
Literally stayed awful
for about a month, maybe six weeks.
It, see, I think it sort of, yeah. Maybe. Mm.
Four weeks. Yeah. Four weeks of like minus 20 at least.
So,
So this is a, a very dense session.
Yeah. So it looks to me like we don't have
any breakouts this time.
Yeah. Um, so I think
if you were to like, interrupt me in this,
particularly in this session, okay.
Um, to restate certain things
or to ask me questions about certain things, so that, like,
just assume that somebody in the room is like afraid
of finance and numbers.
Yeah. Um, that's how, how I think that'd be helpful.
Okay. That's how I am starting.
I'm just like, I'm starting saying, uh,
we're shifting our focus to the financial side of things.
And for some of us, this is really exciting
and for a good chunk of us, it's the worst.
Mm-hmm. Uh, or like much less appealing.
Um, and so we want keep, or
Intimidating is probably the right word.
Yeah. Uh, so we wanna keep things as practical
and straightforward as possible.
Um, so maybe I'll, I'll just ask folks
to also don't be afraid to, to put, um,
questions in the chat, uh mm-hmm.
So that we can sort of take pauses at regular intervals
to make sure that we're, um, unpacking those pieces.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
Is there a way you wanna be interrupted?
I
probably just, just asking clarifying questions.
Uh, especially if I start, especially when we get
to the point where we're like going over formulas and stuff.
Okay. Um, or, or acronyms.
Um, which I'll, um, I'll No doubt do.
Uh, so I think like the first few
slides are not that complicated.
It's really when we get to like, slide 20 ish and
after, um, that it gets a little bit more, yeah.
So like the second, the financial performance management
hierarchy part.
Okay.
Um, I found like, re-watching this particular,
like this cohort three one, like it was tricky to follow.
Mm-hmm. Um, with Dale.
Yeah. I didn't see Dale's. I did this in the beta cohort.
Okay. And then Dale,
Dale changed it a little bit in the second one.
'cause Dale's background, he was a cpa a Okay.
In a CPA firm. Um, looking at some of the changes,
it looks more CPA Aish.
Okay. Um, um, I might,
Yeah, I, I just say like, starting around slide 23,
like, uh, absolutely.
Pause every few session, a few slides even before then,
and just say, Hey, again, if you have any questions,
please put it in the chat.
You know, in this session, we're not gonna have a breakout,
so it'd be great to, to break up some of the, the slides.
Um, and then, uh, it's probably starting at slide 23,
especially, uh, let's look at, uh, you know, just kind
of restating things, asking, clarifying questions.
Okay.
You'll be sharing your screen.
No, I was, uh,
if you could share the screen, is that okay?
Okay. That's fine.
I am letting people in. Is that okay with you?
Yeah. Let me just share my screen quickly.
All right. Can you see my screen?
I sure can. And I am just turning, uh,
moving the waiting room.
Hello. Hello everyone.
Good morning. Good morning. Good afternoon.
Good morning. Good afternoon. Good evening.
Good evening. Yes. Yeah, I know we're,
we're tipping into Tuesday for some of you.
Nice to see everyone. Hope everyone had a restful weekend.
Just giving everyone a moment to get settled.
All right. Are you good to get, uh, to get going, Hayden?
Yeah, let's do it. All right.
Hello everyone, and, uh, welcome
to session six of Empower Labs.
I'm happy to see you all
and hope you're having a great start to your week.
Uh, today we're shifting our focus, uh,
onto the financial side of your business.
Uh, I recognize for some of you, this is the really I,
uh, exciting stuff.
And for others, it's really intimidating.
Uh, our aim is to keep things in this session as practical
and straightforward as possible, providing you with tools
that deliver useful, uh, and concrete answers.
Uh, but for those of you
who do find this material a little bit more challenging, um,
I really want to encourage you to use, uh,
the chat function today.
We're gonna be taking, uh, regular intervals to, uh,
regular pauses to just sort of look over your questions
and make sure that we're answering everything, uh,
appropriately, uh,
because it's a very, this is a very dense sec, uh, session.
Uh, you don't need to be a math whiz for today,
and you're not leaving a certified accountant.
But, uh, we do want you to walk away
with a solid understanding of, um, uh, the key levers
that drive your, uh, business' success.
Our quick check-in for today is that we are in the middle
of, uh, this cohort.
Uh, we are at session six of 12.
Uh, we're at the halfway point.
We've been, uh, systematically working
through the empower, uh, framework.
We've covered execution market access,
and today we're moving on to profitability.
Uh, we've been building our foundation With that,
everything else sort of sits on, uh, so today is, uh,
p our profitability
where things really start to come together.
Um, this is what makes it possible to, uh, keep, uh, going
and to eventually, uh,
exit your business if that's your goal.
Uh, before we begin, let's, uh,
quickly align on the three layers of, uh, business processes
that we've been discussing.
Uh, today we're gonna be looking at the foundational
or enabling processes layer, uh, specifically financial, um,
performance management.
This is crucial because this layer is
what supports everything else.
And mastering this enabling processes layer means
that you gain clearer visibility into your position, uh,
allowing you to make well-informed decisions
and, uh, confidently pursue investment
or scaling opportunities.
Alright, uh, we're gonna do a quick milestone check-in.
I'm gonna launch a poll poll here for you.
Just give me one moment.
Uh, so hoping to see where everyone is up to this point.
Uh, you should have created your UVP version one
and, uh, run your Market to lead assessment, uh,
analyzed your unit economics and created level one
and level two SOPs for market to lead.
Um, we had a couple of optional exercises as well, uh,
and that was to research competitors
and, uh, look at some comp, uh, content marketing material.
All right, though, it looks like, uh,
the great news is everyone has started.
So, woo-hoo. Congratulations.
Uh, here you go.
Uh, and, um, uh,
and no one has quite completed all of the exercises yet.
Uh, I'm gonna stop sharing that.
All right.
Yeah, I guess I will take it from here.
Okay. Um, yeah, today we're gonna go over, uh,
financial performance management, uh,
specifically the seven financial levers, the
financial performance management hierarchy, specifically
for sort of small businesses.
Uh, and we're gonna give some reference examples.
Uh, we're also gonna talk, obviously, in each
of these sections, how we can use AI to, uh,
accelerate the creation of a lot of the process here, uh,
as well as benchmark things.
We, we'll come across that word a lot.
So let's start with the, uh, seven financial leavers.
Um, but just some, some quick context.
Uh, so I, I buy businesses, uh, professionally,
and this is actually the first thing
that we do when we buy a business.
Um, this is 100% of the businesses.
This is the first lever that we pull before anything else.
Uh, and we put in a lot of these systems, literally day one.
And the reason for that is small businesses, uh, kind of,
they, they live and die on, on cash flow management.
Um, and outside of that, you know, when we buy businesses,
we often have some debt, uh, involved in the purchases too.
So that, that makes it even more important.
Um, financial performance management directly impacts
your business valuation.
So if you ever do want to exit your business at any point,
uh, it's having the systems in place,
obviously make it very attractive for the acquirer.
Um, but more than anything,
it reduces financial risk in your company.
Uh, the number one thing that we're gonna return
to a lot here is, uh, never running outta money.
So here are the seven levers.
We'll go over each of them one at a time.
Uh, the first one is increasing your prices.
The second one is increasing your volume.
The third is lowering your costs.
Uh, so your cogs in particular, cost of good sold.
Your fourth is reducing your operating expenses.
Uh, your fifth is reducing your inventory.
If you carry inventory, uh,
your sixth is getting paid faster
and your seventh is delaying your payments.
So let's start with number one. And this is actually, again,
this is the number one lever we pull on.
I would say 100% of the businesses we've bought.
We've increased prices within the first
six months of acquisition.
And of those, I would say 95% we've done so
without any, um, absolutely any blowback, uh,
from, from customers.
And this has always been something that's, I think,
emotionally difficult.
Uh, and it's actually harder just to convince your team, uh,
to increase your, your prices.
And that's really the challenge here.
Um, but it's extremely, extremely important.
We'll, we'll go over why.
So first, some, some tips on, you know,
how you should raise your prices.
Uh, generally speaking, we like to test it
with new customers, not, you know, pre-existing customers.
Um, pricing should be value based, right?
So we don't want to, we don't want to use sort of time
and materials based pricing.
Uh, we want to base it on, you know, customer outcomes.
Uh, if Coca-Cola sold based on time
and materials, it would probably cost 12 cents a Coke.
Um, Starbucks sold it probably be 12 cents a coffee.
Um, pricing should be, uh, part of a process, uh,
a regularly review process, uh, where
you, especially when any new increases in cost
for materials, uh, get sent onto you,
that you send it back onto the customer
as quickly as possible.
Uh, so any construction business, for example, that we buy,
we, we actually put in a monthly price review, um,
during COVID.
Uh, we had it even more frequent simply
'cause of all the supply chain issues.
Um, and then the other other aspect of pricing is
that you can bundle strategically.
We'll, we'll get to that a little bit more on how you,
on your perception in the market.
Uh, but this is how you get towards becoming a category
of one or closer to a category of one,
as we've mentioned in previous sessions.
Uh, even if what you're selling is somewhat commoditized,
I'm curious of the, of the people here, uh,
when was the last time you raised your prices?
Every year. Annually?
Yes. Mm-hmm.
Looking at the chat, it looks like, uh,
a couple folks are saying, uh, annual increase one year ago.
Uh, okay. Two years for one person.
So I would, um, one of the things that you'll,
you'll get this outta the homework as well,
but one of the things that you can do here is each
of the levers that we talk about, I really encourage you to,
uh, use sort of this fractional CFO prompt, uh,
which is not even much of a prompt.
It's really just saying, act as my CFO
and let's chat about my business
along with the master prompt.
Um, but ask it about price increases.
Ask it about, ask Claude about, uh, what should, uh,
trigger a price increase.
Um, I personally increase prices at a minimum twice a year,
uh, depending on the business,
even on a service-based business.
And if I'm not increasing prices,
I might be changing terms slightly.
Um, one thing to, to be aware of is, and,
and I'm sure everyone knows this, but,
but sometimes it's good just to see the math again
and be reminded, but a 1% price increase is not equal.
A 1% profit increase, the lower your gross margin, uh,
in a business, the higher the,
the price increase from a profitability, uh, perspective is,
um, so price increases are the absolute fastest path
to profitability improvement.
And they're also fairly easy to undo.
It's, it's not, it's not a, you could, I,
I have in the past increased prices only
to reduce them again, three months later
with very little blow back.
So it's not like, uh, you're, you're making, you know,
permanent, taking a permanent risk.
Uh, and again, very important, your,
your unique value proposition directly
impacts your pricing power.
And so, the reason I put this session after the marketing
and brand equity session is you'll understand that
in certain cases, you may choose to tailor your
ICP to something a little bit more specific.
And by doing so, can ultimately, you know,
greatly increase your pricing.
Right? As an example, if we have a construction company,
and one, one of the things that we looked at in this company
was examples of good jobs versus bad jobs.
And, and so with every leadership team in our companies,
that's something we do in our first offsite workshop
as we look at good jobs versus bad jobs financially.
And we, we try to figure out why the bad jobs,
the low gross margin jobs were bad,
and why the good jobs were good.
And in some instances, we found that, you know,
certain segment, certain segments by industry, uh,
were extremely good, or certain sizes
of job were extremely good, right?
And in, in more than one instance, we chose to
actually double down on that, specialize in that segment,
uh, and actually increase our pricing by being basically one
of the few specialists locally in that segment.
Um, in that instance, like let's say a construction company
can go from a 20% gross margin to literally a 40%
or 35% gross margin, um, which is just a absolutely massive
increase to overall profitability.
Um, because not only does it increase its prices,
but over time it also gets more efficient, right?
Because it gets better at doing that specialized work.
Um, so quick example,
We have one question in the chat.
I just, if we could take one pause. Of course. Yep. Yeah.
So, uh, Jonas is asking,
what's more important from your point of view?
Increase in prices, uh, or conditions as often as possible,
or simpl simplicity versus automation aligned contracts.
Sorry, what was the second option?
Uh, Jonas, do you wanna ask your question? Um,
Sure. Uh, so
basically, what do you think is more important
change in pricing and conditions regularly,
or, uh, simplicity, automation, you know, aligned contracts,
basically to take out the complexity?
I can already imagine, based on what you said,
but wanna, wanna hear your, wanna hear your take?
I mean, they're, they're both important.
It, it's not, it's not one or the other. Um, mm-hmm.
I, I'd say both. Uh, what has, I'd say pricing has a larger,
it's a, it's lower hanging fruit.
Mm-hmm. Right? It's, it's probably the least amount
of effort for the most of amount of, like,
of impact from a profitability perspective.
Um, so that's why it's the first thing
that we do when we buy a company.
Um, but I would say both.
Okay. Okay. Appreciate it.
Yep. So, uh, simple example here.
I, again, some, sometimes people, I mean,
I think everybody knows this, but it's good to see it again.
Let's say you have a, a, a business
where your main product is sold
for a hundred dollars, right?
A hundred dollars in revenue, your cost of goods on
that is $75, meaning you have 25% gross margin
and $25 of gross profit.
A 10% price increase,
literally is a 40% profitability increase, right?
Your gross margin grow grows to almost 32%.
And most of the time, you know, more than a, you know,
I would say most of our, our price increases start at about
the 25% when we buy a company.
And most companies that we buy are similar in
that they probably raise their prices
once every year or two.
Um, the only exception I would say is, is you need
to be aware of what, when increasing prices, you need
to be aware of what prices are true.
Uh, shoppable prices and com, like commoditized prices.
So, as an example, in, uh, plumbing
or in really any kind of home service business,
there might be like a dispatch fee, right?
The, the initial fee to send someone out to go to the work.
And that may, that is a highly competitive price
that people shop easily.
But once you're actually there and doing the work,
and you, you know, figure out what needs to be done,
and you diagnose it, at that point, it's, you know, most of
that price is not easily shoppable, right?
It's because often it's not, you need a new, um,
furnace, right?
Often it's, you need this repair or this specific repair.
Um, and so in those cases, you'll find that, you know,
if you end up doing some kind of time
and materials pricing, you can often have, you know,
in a home service business in 65%, um,
margins on labor and maybe 35% margins on materials.
So it's important to understand which of my prices
that I'm putting out are actually
very shoppable, uh, and which are not.
And those that are not shoppable, uh, I'd say
that there's a lot of room and
mad I'm not watching the chat.
So anytime, um, there's a question,
just feel free to interrupt me.
Will do. So again, if we,
if we work our way from the bottom up, uh, from bad to good,
in my opinion, um, commodity pricing, uh, you have
a lot of competition, a lot of margin pressure,
very difficult to be the cheapest, uh,
without significant volume.
Um, next level up, I'd say is, is just some sort of feature
or service advantage.
So just a small premium over the commoditized options.
The next level up would be a very clear differentiation.
So I would say a moderate premium over alternatives, uh,
in this case is in this case,
you could also be getting into territories of,
of maybe being one of two options, right?
Or one of three options.
Um, because let's say you specialize,
you end up specializing more on, you know,
your most pro profitable segment.
And then finally you have this category of one,
which is premium pricing
with no direct comparison whatsoever, uh, which can be done
through a combination of this lower one of differentiation
with bundling often, right?
We are the only ones who do this, this, this,
and this other thing, right?
And nobody else does the other thing.
And because of that, you can command higher prices, um,
you can defend higher prices.
Um, curious here, where do you feel,
out of these four levels, where do you feel
your main product or service lives?
And do you see a path towards category of one?
Nancy is saying clear, uh, differentiation for now.
Uh, we also, uh, have someone here saying, uh, between two
and three, uh, but not a clear path to category one.
Do you have a competitor if there's not a clear
path to category one?
Are there any competitors, as you looked at, that seem
to be closer to that?
Not that I can name offhand.
Okay. Might be an interesting, uh,
Claude competition research.
Uh, if you did the optional homework in the last,
in the last session, might be a good thing to look at.
Uh, we've got a couple folks who are, uh,
moving towards clear differentiation as well.
Great.
So it, I, I'd like to add something AI based
for each of these levers.
Um, so this first one, uh, I, I would say asking ai,
uh, what should trigger pricing increases?
Uh, should you increase your prices?
And, uh, also doing research on this differentiation
side, all excellent, uh, uses of ai, uh,
both Claude and Chat, GBT
and I I check both are excellent at benchmarking on pricing.
Um, you know,
historically benchmarking has been a fairly expensive
endeavor to, to buy different types of reports.
Uh, but I, I have found
that they're quite good at benchmarking, let's say,
gross margin, um,
and cogs across all sorts of very specific verticals.
Um, so also a great thing to check,
but I would check with both, um,
because sometimes Chacha, BT has a better answer.
Lever number two, and this is probably the lever most people
think about when they think I need more money, is
to increase your volume.
Um, so obviously you can increase your volume by,
by simply getting more customers.
Uh, but that's the more expensive
way of increasing your volume.
Uh, so the first thing, instead of
pouring more leads at the top of your funnel, uh,
the first things you should look at is
optimizing your sales funnel.
So focusing on conversion rates at each stage
of your funnel, uh, rather than just pouring more leads in
that top, uh, part of, you know, last week's session, uh,
went over some of that.
And part of the next session is gonna go over more of that,
uh, cross-selling more to existing customers.
So we talked about the five Rs, right?
And, and outlining a customer journey
and figuring out how can I, uh, basically resell, how can I,
um, either sell more of the same product
or service to the same customer,
or sell, you know, cross-sell, upsell,
downsell, different things.
One of the beauties, uh, beautiful things about, uh, ai,
and we're gonna go into this in session nine, is
that it's now easier than ever to create, um, additional
services specifically, um, in order
to either upsell or downsell.
Like what, what used
to be probably a six month process
can now be a two week process.
Uh, if you, you know, really leverage your use of ai,
um, referral programs, right?
So again, another one of the Rs out,
when you outline your customer journey,
what's the ascension point that best asks, uh, allows you
to ask for a referral, right?
Whether or not you are just asking
and, you know, not giving anything,
or whether you actually have an official program
or you're, you know, giving a
commission or some kind of benefit.
Uh, and then obviously, if, if you do need to,
or your last choice is throwing more money
or throwing more output at the top of the funnel.
Um, but
before you do that, you really need to monitor your,
your CAC versus your, your customer value, uh, to ensure
that, you know, you're, you're in a safe place to do so.
And the the last thing I'll say about that,
and we'll return to it, again, going back to this concept of
don't die, don't run out of, don't run outta money, uh, is
new marketing initiatives.
You should assume that they will take time
and money to work.
Um, and you should always ensure
that you have enough money in the bank, right?
To, uh, comfortably carry that cost
before you invest in it.
So I would always say, do these other,
these first three things here
before you start, uh,
pouring more money into getting more leads,
unless you have a solid, you know, at minimum of four months
of burn in the bank after the investment.
Any questions on, uh, lever number two before I move on?
Okay. Lever number three is
to lower your cost of goods sold.
So this is fairly obvious.
Um, renegotiate supplier contracts, eliminate waste
and processes, automate repetitive tasks.
Obviously, that piece is something
we're gonna look at a lot here.
Uh, and then especially today,
do a make versus buy analysis regularly on,
on all the things that you're currently, um,
spec specifically on all the things
that you're currently outsourcing.
Because now doing things in house,
especially things like software, um,
is incredibly cheap, right?
Um, I replaced all my CRMs
and all of my businesses with in-house solutions
that were made in a weekend, uh, because of ai, right?
That, that eliminates probably 30 KA yearend costs
for like Salesforce or HubSpot.
Um, and that's the type of project now that used
to be like a two year endeavor,
or a one year endeavor, um, totally impractical to do.
Um, but today is literally, you know, two weeks max.
Obviously, that's not a cogs example, that's a opex example.
But
actually, this one is also a great thing
to just ask AI about, right?
Again, I, I would highly encourage
that everyone review the deck after the fact,
and as they kind of go through specifically
that fractional CFO prompt ask on each single, single lever,
Hey, on my products
or service, what are some ways
that I could reduce my cost of goods sold?
Specifically, how can I use AI to do that?
What would be the next steps?
Uh, lever number four is reducing your
operating expenses, your overhead.
Um, something that I actually have
as a quarterly process is to actually look at
how can I take, uh, a fixed expense
and turn it into a variable one, uh, which is really
what finance should be doing a lot of the time.
Um, if you currently have, uh, so tie your compensation
to variable success as much as you can.
You can, and try to align, pay, um, with that performance
through bonuses or profit sharing,
and also try to align, pay
with revenue generating events for you.
Um, it makes your life a lot easier if you align pay
with bonuses that are not revenue generating
and maybe are two months away from revenue generating.
It can affect your cashflow negatively.
Uh, I look at monthly software as annual costs.
So if you have, and,
and you should have, um, a budget
approval process, right?
Where maybe, uh, directors
or managers have a certain amount of money
that they can spend without your, without looking
for approval, uh, from their manager.
I look at any monthly software cast as an annual cost, um,
simply because there's,
otherwise, there's a ton of creep, um, that comes in as, as,
you know, people start forgetting about subscriptions,
uh, leverage temp workers strategically, I,
if a, a great book on this is, um,
exponential organizations.
Uh, they talk quite a bit about this,
but wherever you can, there's sort of a new breed
of business that leverages sort of temp workers.
Um, another interesting, uh, thing
to potentially talk to Claude about.
And then finally, you should definitely have a process
to just audit your recurring expenses at least quarterly.
Um, I, I'd probably do it more frequently.
And again, here's a great way you can probably look at some
of the, your software expenses and, and you could ask Claude
or even prototype yourself with something like AI Studio,
um, to understand, you know,
is there a $10,000 a year expense you could entirely
eliminate, um, through a couple days of vibe coding.
Lever five is only applicable
to businesses within inventory.
Um, but it's reduce your inventory.
Um, so different ways to do this, right?
You can do just in time ordering.
Uh, you can complete your projects faster, uh,
you can improve demand forecasting, um, again,
only applies to businesses with an inventory,
so I won't spend too much time there.
Lever number six is get paid faster.
So this is basically improving your, uh,
accounts receivable process, right?
Um, huge thing
that you can do if you're not doing it already,
is collecting more upfront in everything that you do, right?
Um, uh, also one of the things
that we change almost immediately, uh, in
probably the majority of the businesses we we buy
is we change the payment structure.
Um, very interesting to see
how ar affects businesses, right?
Especially if you look like inventory, heavy,
heavy businesses, you can see that a business can make,
you know, on, on paper, be profitable, but run out of money
and go bankrupt, um, because of this.
Um, so tighten your payment terms.
So moving to net 15
or better, uh, instead of standard net 30, um,
ob obviously automate billing and collections.
If you're taking checks, stop doing that.
Uh, and then accept,
uh, multiple payment methods.
And you can look into financing options like Klarna.
Um, and similar, especially if in your, in the US
lever number seven is two is the opposite.
It's delaying your payments, right?
So this is optimizing your account's payable process.
Um, you need to be careful with this
because you're effectively, um,
you're, it is a balancing act, um,
and you don't want to abuse people too much.
Uh, so how you communicate it is, is extremely important.
Um, if you're looking at
employees, um, you know, it's the best thing for you is
to pay them as infrequently as possible.
Often the best thing for them is to be paid
as frequently as possible.
Um, hourly employees in many of the companies that we buy,
uh, are paid weekly, and we often switch to biweekly, uh,
and then salaried employees.
And most of the companies we buy are paid weekly
or biweekly, and sometimes we'll shift to biweekly
or monthly, um,
pay vendors with credit cards whenever possible.
Uh, this is like a, even,
like a 2% cashback can make a pretty large difference.
Um, we've had a lot of businesses where, um, you know,
effectively the GM salary was almost entirely paid based
on, on cashback.
Uh,
and then always be aware
that cheaper isn't always better with all your vendors.
Uh, and often terms, uh, can be better than price.
So you, you may have a great option
that does not allow you to delay your AP at all,
but is 5% cheaper.
Uh, whereas you have another option that's, you know,
maybe 10% more expensive,
but you can delay your AP 60, 90 days.
Um, if you actually model that out
or get clogged to model it out for you, you'll find
that from a cashflow perspective,
the ladder is often better.
Quick q and a, this is dense, uh, it's gonna get denser.
Um, any questions before we move on?
Dawn, I see you had a question in the chat.
I don't know if you wanna speak that into the room.
Yeah, sure. Uh, I'm just, uh, one
of the little tidbits you tossed our way is, uh, do it,
you know, uh, building your CRM in-house,
and, uh, I'm going, oh, I wonder how you do that.
What's CDI
Would say, uh, actually we're in,
we're in limbo right now.
Uh, we, uh, we've been un unhappy with FileMaker, and so,
Okay, It got rejected
and basically there isn't one, so we're gonna, we need one.
And I am looking around wondering what I gonna do about it.
Yeah. So I, I would ask Claude to help you with, uh, a,
a roadmap and a, and a project specification, uh,
for creating this, uh,
I probably wouldn't make it in Claude there.
I would actually go to, to Gemini
and go to AI studio to make your first draft.
Um, but do the, the project spec first.
'cause Claude has your master prompt understands everything
you need, have it ask you questions, right?
At least, you know, explain what you need
and have asked you at least five questions,
one at a time standard way.
And then take that project spec, spec
and load it into AI Studio.
Uh, you will be amazed with what you get back
as a first prototype.
Um, it'll give you a good idea as to whether that's doable.
I'm guessing it is, um, the, you know,
the functionality if you need within your CRM, let's say
you need to be making calls within it, right?
So, or, or you need
to be making texts within it, things like that.
Um, then you probably need
to have some integrations like Twilio integrations.
If you don't need that, then it's a very, very simple,
if it's more just like a, I need records, I need emails,
I need, um, you know, some level of automation.
Uh, we did our CRM in Airtable. Um-huh.
So, and it was, it was done in a weekend by one
of our guys who's not a developer.
Well,
That's, uh, fabulous.
And I, I, I'm familiar with Airtable,
and they, it's amazing how simple, uh, the, the actual use
of it is by some of these, uh, contractors.
You know, they, they just need it. Mm-hmm.
They don't even have their pipeline, uh, clarified.
And so that's, that'd be a primary thing.
And, and then, uh, communicating with clients, uh,
and prospects via email, follow up reminders, et cetera.
You know, it's just not rocket science, right?
Mm-hmm. Yeah.
I don't know what those companies are gonna do.
Salesforce and HubSpot, or Yeah.
They're gonna get their asses kicked,
Uh, clearly.
Okay. Thanks for mentioning that.
But Hayden, don't you think it would take a long time
for those enterprise levels to unwind?
I mean, think of the, the training
and the, uh, just onboarding that needs to go
through these big, massive companies.
We know last weekly took a big hit when Claude Code mm-hmm.
Came out, but don't you see their, it being a, a challenge
for those big companies?
A hundred percent. Uh, so I would say like,
the larger the company, the more ingrained they are in,
in the legacy system.
Um, but if you think like, overall,
they don't have positive net revenue retention, right?
Most, most of them, and all
of the smaller companies coming in, like,
let's say Salesforce for example, it makes its money
by bringing companies, smaller companies in
and having expansion and net revenue retention over time.
Those smaller companies are not gonna sign up to,
to Salesforce in the next, you know, starting now, basically
because there's so many other options.
Um, either they can do it themselves,
or there's now new AI first CRMs that, you know,
drive the cost down to nothing.
Um, so yeah,
I don't think they're gonna be wiped out overnight.
Um, but I think they're gonna have to reinvent themselves,
uh, in order to, to bring on especially the
smaller, new clients.
And your story, Hayden, about, uh, not needing
as many licenses, uh, was pretty fascinating.
Yeah. I mean, I don't even need any licenses anymore,
but, um, yeah, if you do, uh, if you have a CRM
and, uh, you have a lot of your actual conversations
with your salespeople happening outside of platform, right?
So let's say having happening on Slack or Telegram
or WhatsApp, um,
and all, all of the reporting is done automatically.
Uh, technically you only need one seat, right?
You only need one seat that's effectively like a sales
manager seat to go in and see reporting, um,
because your actual salespeople
don't ever log into your CRM anymore.
They just communicate with an agent. So
What's your, uh, what's your go-to on the recording,
uh, of these calls?
Uh, we do it ourselves now, like
with a custom, uh, solution.
Uh, any of them are fine though.
Uh, you know, we did, I think the,
the workflow I shared on tia's channel was we use bubbles.
A lot of people like using Otter.
A lot of people like using granola.
A lot of people use Fathom. They're all the
same as far as I'm concerned.
Um, Go with whatever's cheapest
and gives you, yeah, I'd say go with whatever,
if you haven't cho chosen something, I would go
with whatever is cheapest.
Plus gives you additional functionality.
Um, so for example, like Crisp,
uh, also gives you like accent removal functionality
and gives you like loom style
functionality, so you could go with that.
Um, it's also one of those ones that, uh, just integrates
with your speakers, so it's not necessarily a bot that goes
to a meeting and needs to be accepted.
Um, which there, there may be some kind of, you know, risk,
um, from a legal perspective
and recording conversations there.
But if you're doing it at least just for your own team,
then I think that's totally fine.
Hayden, were there? Yep.
Question, um, did I understand, uh, correctly you
onset concepted with, with cloud,
so the product spec specifications,
then the prototype development was done by
AI studio from Google, so Gemini Yep.
Environment, and Yep.
You ended up implementing it in with Airtable?
Yep. Okay.
Yeah, so a little hack
for anyone who's vibe coding, um, there,
if you wanna vibe code a prototype that you want
to use internally with your team
and you wanna make it work like same day, uh, you can vibe,
code something that works for you.
And ultimately what you need is like a save
and load feature, right?
Almost like the old days of computing.
Um, and what you can do is you can just ask it
to do A-J-S-O-N import
and export feature,
which is effectively a save and load feature.
Um, and then you literally have a working prototype
that is usable by your team within a couple hours by doing
that, it's just they have to remember to hit save
and have to remember to hit load.
Um, the next level up of complexity,
but it's still very simple, is to link it
with Airtable, right?
Airtable is a database, it's a very visual, easy
to access database, right?
You don't need to be technical, uh, and Claude
or whichever tool you use can walk you
through the integration very simply.
Um, and the nice thing is Airtable also has a pretty good
called Omni pretty good AI chat.
So you can use that AI chat in A CRM, for example,
in our CRMI never look at the CRMI just ask Omni, you know,
look up this customer, right?
Um, or show me a report of all the customers
that hit X criteria.
So that's, that's I'd say the next level.
And that may might add a day or so in implementation
and still does not require someone technical.
And now you have automatic cloud-based saving
and loading, um, going the full, going the full way
of like actually properly deploying
it to the cloud.
Probably it adds technical, um,
like a, a new technical requirement
that probably requires a programmer
and probably adds two to three weeks to the process.
So I wouldn't do that
unless you are really selling, um, a product
and, and basically selling, selling this product to,
to a customer base that needed, needed that level of scale.
Hey, Nancy, unless of course you have the budget,
Uh, Nancy's just asking if you can repeat the name
of the recording program that you mentioned.
Oh, crisp, uh, yeah, Chris Crisp is neat. K-R-I-S-P.
I use it, I'm a fan.
It's neat because it's, uh, it's actually a,
it was originally a noise canceler for your mic,
so you know, you have like, noise canceling headphones.
I I often work on a treadmill
and the treadmill's kind of loud.
And so I wanted something
that like removed the background noise
and it worked really well.
And then they turned it into like an accent removal tool,
which was really interesting.
And obviously the meeting recorder is built in,
and I think it has screen sharing stuff now too.
I'm not affiliated.
Okay. Um, financial performance management.
So one of the homeworks you're gonna have,
like we've done in the past, is you're gonna get a visual
diagram of what, you know,
strong financial performance management
looks like in a company.
Um, as usual, what you'll get is probably
what is appropriate for a company with about,
let's say 50 plus employees.
Uh, if you are smaller than that, um,
you can probably ask it, um,
after the fact, you know,
what is appropriate for the size of my company?
Um, I would separate all finance
and kind of into, into two different buckets.
So we have hygiene, which is more
of the day-to-day operational act activities.
And then we have the insights piece, uh, which is more
around, uh, reporting and strategy.
And the insights is where those seven
levers we talked about live.
Um, as you create your process, you will be creating process
for both, um, over the longer term.
Uh, and typically in a company, you know,
the hygiene would be done by a combination of like a book,
a bookkeeper or a controller, right?
Um, whereas the insights would be done by yourselves
or by a CFO.
Um, you know, I think CFOs, again, the,
the, the trend, if you're a private company, um,
without investors, uh,
I see the trend probably being moving away from any need
for CFOs, um, and moving a lot towards the usage of ai.
So transactionally, I, you know, I don't see
most of what you'll be able to implement with AI is,
uh, workflows into your existing systems
and automation, into your existing systems.
Uh, and, and probably if you go
and research it, uh, there will likely be new versions, um,
new niche down versions of SaaS that will be lower cost.
Uh, and I'm, I'm sure that's gonna,
that's coming out every day.
Um, I'm assuming most people here
run on QuickBooks Zero, et cetera.
What, what systems do you use for, for books
So far? We've got, uh,
everyone is saying QuickBooks.
Yep. Viewpoint.
So again, something you can easily work with,
with Claude Cloud, knows all.
Uh, talk to Claude about, um, specific hygiene items
and how you can introduce, uh, automation in your company,
uh, through this hygiene items.
I'll be introducing a prompt in session nine,
session 10, sorry.
Uh, which is around, uh, basically
telling AI about your technology stack, um,
and figuring out how to implement that into workflows.
So maybe we'll wait until then
before you do that,
some things I'm curious if you're doing, uh,
this is something that we make, uh, a requirement, uh,
within every business that we buy, no matter how small.
Uh, so first is cashflow projections,
so usually a 13 week cashflow, um, preview,
always running on that.
Uh, next is an MBRA monthly business review.
Uh, this is something that used to take, so our,
our structure was, we had a, so we had holding companies.
The holding company usually had a CFO.
I have three holding companies,
and then we had portfolio companies
underneath those were too small to afford A CFO,
and so they usually had a controller.
And effectively,
after we bought a company, we kind
of train the controller typically over a couple months,
and a couple tries on, on a monthly business review process,
which was specifically, um, you know, outside of just,
you know, income statements, balance sheets, um, ar, uh,
and AP aging reports.
It would be a, a slide deck.
So a simple slide deck showing all
of the important financial metrics, uh, target
versus actual on a monthly basis.
And this used to take probably, you know,
the better part of 10 days
for the controller to put together properly.
Um, and then the CFO would have to review it
before it was actually then, uh, presented to, uh,
the leadership team and the board.
And that process today is made with workflows
and AI is made way, way faster.
Um, you know, un easily an afternoon.
Um, so if you're not currently doing an mbr RI highly highly
recommend you do, and you talk to Claude about
what should be in the MDR, um,
and exactly how to go about getting all that DA data.
Um, just that outta curiosity.
Well, I'll, I'll finish the rest. Income statement analysis.
Uh, obviously you're, you're really,
you're comparing budgets versus actuals, um,
in your income statement, uh, and then AR
and AP aging reports that should be done, you know, weekly,
um, just to make sure, uh,
specifically on accounts receivable, uh,
that you're collecting your money quickly and efficiently.
So I'm curious how many people
here have an MBR structure in their company?
I mean, if, if you do, maybe put it in the chat,
and if you don't, then I'm almost then don't,
Looks like some folks do, uh, Nancy saying
that since cohort
one, more or less working.
Well,
So for those that don't, uh, this is again,
very low hanging fruit, something
that Claude can help you with.
Um, and,
and something that makes a real, real difference, not only
for your own analysis, uh,
but for just, you know, accountability
and, um, visibility for your leadership team.
And if cash is tight, and,
and for me tight is like, let's say you have under,
under four months of operating expenses in the bank, um,
then you, you should definitely be having like a 13 week
cashflow statement that you're reviewing weekly.
Um, if anything, it's really just to, uh,
remind you, because often you'll want to, you know,
take on certain bets and certain things.
It's just to remind you not to, um, you know, to have a,
a set of rules in place to say, you know, don't spend money,
uh, that you don't have.
And sometimes that constraint is very helpful
and makes you more innovative,
especially on the customer acquisition side.
Uh, these are some things that you know, you out, honestly,
out of these things, the, the only thing
that I would really recommend out of these items
for every company would be just the cash conversion cycle
tracking on a quarterly basis, um, especially
for like receivable heavy businesses.
And then this, I'd say is probably quarterly to annual,
annual being the least.
Frequently you should do this, I would be actual budget
and variance tracking, right?
Usually that's a quarterly review in a company.
Um, so actually setting a budget for each, uh, division
or department in the company, uh,
and then seeing the variance in actuals versus the budget,
uh, the burned runway calculation.
So you just calculate your cash divided
by your monthly opex, um,
and determine
how much runway you have if things were to drop to zero.
Um, and then having separate levels of, uh,
p and l ownership, uh, is also important.
Okay, so some metrics, I'm going to
explain some things that might be, uh,
everyone might find really, really basic.
Um, but just for the, uh, for the sake of those that may,
may not know them, uh, I'm gonna go over them quickly.
So I, what we always teach our companies when,
when running a p and l is we kind of start
with revenue at the top, right?
I think everyone knows what revenue is.
Then we talk about cogs, right?
Which is the actual, uh, cost of goods sold.
So therefore, like the variable amount, um,
the variable cost associated with the revenue, um,
that pre that creates gross profit.
Um, your gross profit margin is a formula.
Here is your revenue minus your cost
of Google sold, divided by your revenue.
Um, EBITDA is your earnings
before interest, taxes, depreciation, amortization.
Um, other people will look at sort of post tax, uh,
pre-tax profit as a number.
I look at EBITDA simply
because we, businesses are traded based on an EBITDA margin,
uh, sorry, an ebitda, uh, multiple.
Um, so understanding your EBITDA
and having a target for your EBITDA is important.
If you ever wanna get liquidity in your business.
Um, understanding your operating expense ratio.
So looking at your opex divided by revenue, a lot
of businesses go really, really way above,
uh, benchmark here.
Uh, and that's why they end up, um,
not being nearly as profitable.
So understanding that, hey, you know, the benchmark, again,
you can ask Claude, what's the, what's a good opex ratio
for a X business, right?
Or a business of my size, or a business like mine.
And it'll tell you, and maybe it says 25%,
and maybe you realize you're at 45%, right?
And now you need to look at, at cost savings.
Um, and then contribution margin, right?
This is your, your unit economic
that we talked about in the last session is one
of the most important, um, metrics in your business.
Uh, obviously the, the higher you get to that category
of one, the higher your contribution margin,
everything else is easier.
Uh, it's important
to understand your contribution margin per product
or service that you have.
Um, um, so I, I mentioned when we buy a business,
we look at good versus bad jobs.
A huge part of what we do is when we identify those bad
jobs, we do price increases on those bad jobs.
Um, and when we identify the good jobs, uh,
we focus and tailor all our marketing on the good jobs and,
and kind of redo a lot
of the brand positioning towards that ICP.
Um, so the, the big thing here,
these are all extremely important numbers.
If you don't understand them, uh, ask Claude to explain it
to you as if you were a 15-year-old.
Um, if you don't know what a good benchmark is, ask Claude,
what's a good benchmark for your business?
It knows your business. Uh, ask Chad GPT as well, uh,
because you may get a slightly, they're trained off
different data sets, you may get a slightly
different answer.
Um, any questions on any of these numbers?
Okay, monthly to quarterly, uh, sort
of business intelligence, uh,
that you should be checking on a monthly to quarterly basis,
uh, is your unit economics analysis,
the stuff we went over last session, uh,
your efficiency metrics.
So specifically, uh, gross profit or EBITDA per employee
and revenue per employee, especially in the age of ai,
this is actually the number that we are looking
to optimize for, right?
As AI makes things more efficient.
Um, obviously looking at budget variance analysis,
and if you don't currently have a budget, making a budget,
um, that would be a great first.
Uh, there's an optional homework today
that has you making a spreadsheet with Claude.
That would be a, if you don't currently have a budget,
that would be a great one to start with.
Um, and then obviously, you know, tracking,
uh, variants over time.
Uh, again, if you ever look at liquidity in your business,
uh, your compound annual growth rate, your cagr, uh,
is, is a important metric for acquirers.
Uh, more strategic modeling
and planning items that you should probably do on a, um,
probably quarterly to annual basis.
Um, I, I, again, I would probably go closer
to quarterly than to annual personally.
So understanding what your breakeven point is, uh,
we talked about that I, I believe last session a bit.
Um, but essentially you need to, to understand, uh,
calculate the point where total costs
and total revenue are equal.
Um, often a company can have really strong
unit economics,
but just not have enough volume to, to hit their break even.
And, and so most often it's a,
it's a actually just a volume problem.
Um, obviously track your growth rate,
revenue concentration risk.
Again, these, all four of these items are big
acquisition metrics.
Um, so the first thing
that any acquirer will look at is revenue concentration.
So if you have, you know, 30, 40%
of your revenue coming from a single customer,
that is a massive red flag for an acquirer.
They will have to structure your deal around that.
And, uh, you, you wanna look at that proactively, um, so
that, you know, it doesn't become a massive risk
that your biggest customer leaves, uh,
and the business, you know, tanks 30, 40% overnight.
Um, so checking that on a
or having your being reminded to check
that even on a quarterly basis, uh,
and sort of planning around that, I think is important.
Um, and like one, one other note here is I,
I've actually found that like some
of the best businesses actually have, uh,
really strong revenue concentration risk, um, simply
because they do good work.
And so their customers continue coming back to them,
and they don't have a process to either,
they don't have a process to bring in new customers
or their strategy.
I've seen this a lot. Their strategy is to,
I have these great customers,
I'm gonna give them the cheapest prices,
and I'm gonna give expensive prices
to the new customers who may not be great.
Um, and all that does, like, I understand the idea
behind it, but all that actually does
to a business is it creates more
and more revenue concentration risk over time.
So you actually need to have the opposite approach, uh,
in order to reduce that risk, right?
You actually need to almost loss leader
and new customers in, um, while understanding
that the value proposition of you providing a great service
and being reliable to a top customer means
that you should actually be higher priced.
A bit of a mindset shift, um, that we often need to teach.
Okay? So these are
all, um, on, on pricing impact.
One thing that you can do, uh, if you're unsure
is go ask Claude.
Um, if you were to increase your prices by 10, 15%,
what would that do, uh, to
the overall profitability of the company?
Um, have Claude also give you strategic
observations after you do your, your, uh,
prompts in the homework, uh, to give you a written summary
of the key findings and actual recommendations.
Um, have Claude compare your metrics to
industry benchmarks as best as you can.
And also try this in chat gt, um, just
because you'll, you may have one better results
from one versus the other.
Um, and then use Claude as a partner,
a thought partner on every investment decision over a
certain amount, right?
You know, may maybe that amount is like over 5%,
uh, or over even 1% of EBITDA or, um,
or over 5% of ebitda, and teach your team to do that.
Um, so specifically, what ru what rules do you have in place
as to whether or not you can make that investment, right,
to ensure that you don't get sort of emotionally
excited about, you know, the potential of something
and take a, a risk that you, you shouldn't, again,
this is a CFO's job, right?
Most, most business owners are the excited, optimistic, uh,
visionary, and the CFO's job is
to haircut everything that they do.
Uh, and if you don't have a cfo, um, asking Claude to put on
that hat and, and haircut your optimism, um,
and, you know, stress test it, uh, is a, a very,
very useful, uh, very, very useful.
And I have, I found that fractional CFOs are,
or Claude on its own,
is significantly better than a $6,000 a month fractional
CFO, uh,
and potentially better than a full-time
200 KA year CFO, depending on your business.
Little break for questions here.
So it looks like we have a couple of questions, uh,
in the chat here.
Uh, Dawn, do you wanna ask your question into the room?
Uh, you know, this is so rich, thank you for,
for sharing with us here, Hayden.
Um, it did get me wondering about, uh, querying, uh,
QuickBooks and, uh, I'm guessing
that you just export reports into, uh,
you know, to feed to Quad.
Is that pretty much how you do it? Yep.
Yep. That's what, that's what we do.
Yeah. Okay. That makes sense.
And then, uh, as you were going through all this stuff,
I'm like, ah, he's got favorite books
on each one of these topics.
I want the list.
Can you help us out with that? Uh
Huh You know, I've actually, I've actually used YouTube
for finance more than books.
I like YouTube. Yeah. Just, just
because it can walk you through, uh, models better, right?
Uh, and often, uh, you know, you can look at a model
and recreate it, or sometimes you can
just download the model directly.
'cause Mo most of ev everything in finance is,
is spreadsheet related.
Um, so I, I would, I would look for, there's, especially in
like the startup community, there's a lot
of great financial YouTube stuff out there
that gives you access to the sheets and everything.
Um, uhhuh, but honestly even better than both is ask
Claude just to walk you through it.
'cause, 'cause Claude can now just
build the spreadsheets for you.
Like you don't, at this point, it's more of a q
and a session that then results at the end of it,
you're like, oh, by the way, can you build that spreadsheet
or build that go-to-market for me?
And it does. Um, so yeah, not, not so much books, uh,
YouTube if you want more explanation,
but honestly I would, I would focus on Claude or chat chip t
or whichever LLM um, Claude for building spreadsheets
is really the only one that does it. Okay.
Uh, this is, uh, this is perfect
and I haven't been completely crazy
'cause I, I've made a lot of progress with YouTube
identifying, um, you know, credible, uh, um, channels,
uh, you know, you have any favorite
channels you want to mention to us?
I'm sure we'll be all ears, but, um,
I'd have to look. I don't
remember the, the names of them. Um, sure.
But, uh, yeah, Midori,
maybe you can remind me. I'll take a look.
Yeah, I'll do that after the session.
Uh, and Christian is, thank you.
Uh, Christian is also just asking, you're mentioning, uh,
chat, GPT and Claude.
Um, what about Gemini?
Yeah, uh, I think anytime I say check multiple lms,
Gemini is on that list as well.
Um, again, they all have different, the main thing here is,
is one of them may have exposure to data sets
that the others don't.
Right. And maybe it, maybe it was data sets
that would've normally be behind a,
a paywall for most customers.
Um, and that's what I found.
So you might, you might have a, you know,
an insurance business, um, and,
and you have a very specific insurance business
and you need benchmark data.
That would only be, you know, something
that you could get from a thousand dollars report.
Um, sometimes Chatt PT has access to those
for whatever reason, right.
Or Gemini might have access to them.
Um, so I, I think it's worth, based on benchmarks,
it's worth checking multiple.
Um, and I mean, you can aggregate the result.
You can determine whether you trust one result more than
another based on asking where it comes
from and checking it out.
Um, but I mean, that's, that's probably second best to,
uh, actually looking at books of your competitors,
which is another option if you ever look at buying business.
That's everything that we have in the chat.
Okay. I had a question
regarding data protection.
So, uh, is there any data that you do not make available
to AI because data protection issues would
show Paradise your business?
So this is up, this is up
to each individual's risk tolerance.
Me personally, um, I always check the terms
of service, right?
To ensure that nothing I'm using
is being used for training data.
So, um, I'm sure I've mentioned this before,
but just as of right now, chat, GPT
and Claude, it's not being used for training data
unless you click the thumbs up
or thumbs down, um, on any, on any chat.
By doing that, you are explicitly giving them permission.
So if you go out and put in your, I dunno, as an example,
if you go out and put in your, you know, annual
your income statement in and it gives you a result
and you thumbs down the result,
you've just shared that data.
Um, so don't do that.
Uh, if you're really concerned,
you may wanna look into enterprise, right?
So Enterprise Claude, uh, ensures
that no data is ever, uh, shared.
Um,
I think, yeah, that, that, that's the main thing.
I think enterprise is probably the safest
bet if you're really concerned.
Um, otherwise keep an eye on the, on the terms of service
and don't thumbs up or thumbs down anything.
And, and if you're trying something new,
Do you have, uh, for your, uh, different companies
the same, uh, enterprise subscriptions
or do you specify it to the business and the industry?
Which AI solution you, uh, implement?
So we, we do almost purely API calls now in our companies.
So what I
what we're teaching in this cohort is the same thing we
teach to our companies as sort of the level one, right?
Which is kind of get the foundation.
Um, and then we usually, we would then move
to either cloud code
or to, um, like a custom integration,
which would be all a API calls.
And in that case, you, you really don't worry about
training, training models, uh, off of your API calls.
So API calls means, uh, it, it will send it
to different LLMs,
Uh, well, whichever LLM, but,
but on the API side, you're there, there are data agreements
that basically say that they, they won't share
or use that any of that data for training.
Um, it's more on the LLM side,
so working directly within Claude
or within chat GPT, um, that you need
to be a bit more concerned about.
Okay, Hayden, thank you, Hayden.
Do you mind just, uh, uh, letting us know
what you mean by API calls?
I,
Uh, so an API call instead
of is basically you're using programming, um, to,
to send a request to an LLM and,
and get the response back, uh, as opposed
to actually like typing it into a model.
Um, and so if you, if you, again,
probably a good thing rather than going over
what an API is probably good to just ask Claude, uh,
and tell me about the difference between, um, an API
and an LLM and I'm sure it would do a much better job than I
could do in the next 10 minutes.
Um, and then understanding, I mean,
we can even later on in
an office hours if people are interested.
I've done quite a bit of work with different APIs now.
Um, if people are curious, we can go over the costs, uh,
and the sort of advantages
and disadvantages of each of the different providers, um,
and some sort of tips and tricks as I've learned
doing this for several months.
Um, overall it's important to understand that
your usage of Claude is heavily subsidized,
uh, by, you know,
the billions of dollars that they have raised.
Same goes with chacha pt.
Um, at this point, everyone in this cohort is a power user
and is costing them a lot of money.
Um, 'cause inference is actually, I, I look,
I think inference is only a 40 to 60% cogs right now.
Um, so it's actually not a great software business, right?
Um, obviously everyone's just trying to grow
and, and take market share.
Uh, if you go to API, you know,
you're now guaranteeing a certain profit margin there.
Um, and it's going to be a bit more expensive than,
you know, your $30 a month cloud subscription.
Um, if you go to, if you go to,
if you end up using cloud code
or end up becoming a true, true power user, uh, you want
to upgrade to a max times 20 account,
which is actually away from teams.
So I have a separate teams account
and a max times 20 account, uh, which is $200 a month
and gives you a almost infinite usage.
Um, but for context,
when I first started doing it, I was on my teams again.
I was paying almost $200 a day, um, in API fees
before I moved over to it, and now it's just 200 a month.
So, little tip, save you some money.
Thank you. That's all the questions we have in the chat.
Okay. So just some
metrics here, um, which we've already gone over, uh,
but I, I'm keeping it here.
Uh, mainly, so as you go over the actual decks
and the homework, these are things that you can bring
to chat GPT and ask or or Claude
and ask about, um, your benchmarks
and, and ask about your numbers.
Okay? Quick example of break even point
for companies that may have volume problems.
Um, if your monthly fixed costs are $20,000,
if your product sells for a thousand dollars,
your variable cost per sale is $400,
your contribution margin is $600, your gross profit
and your break even point would be 20,000 divided by 600
or 34 sales per month.
So understanding what this number is
and making that a, a clear target if there's ever months
that you don't hit it, um, is quite important.
And like I said, you can have a extremely high margin
business that is unprofitable
'cause you just don't have the break even point,
which means you either need
to reduce your monthly fixed costs,
or you need to bring in more sales typically, um,
or you need to increase your profit margin.
Um, efficiency metrics, uh, again, great thing to be
starting to track, especially in this day
and age going forward, right?
Um, is what is your gross profit
or your EBITDA per employee.
Um, so one of the numbers I will be very curious about from
everyone here in 12 months is how much does
that number go up, right?
Because through automation, you're able to, uh, do more
with less, right?
Maybe that means replacing headcount, um, with automation,
maybe that just means, uh, not hiring more, uh,
and doing more with less.
Um, in one of my companies, we are probably,
we reduced from 200 k, um, monthly burn
in opex to 40 5K,
and we can still service just as much as, as we did before.
Uh, and that's, that was in a six month period,
and that's all just through automation and workflows and,
and it's probably some bloat, right?
But even that bloat probably wouldn't have been an
identified with that ai, um,
OPEX ratio, we talked about that already.
Customer lifetime value is an interesting one.
Um, I don't love this number.
I, I, that's why I put the 90 day customer value,
uh, in the previous session.
I, I vastly prefer that number
because customer lifetime value can be misleading.
Um, and you often don't have the time, uh,
or the runway to optimize for it
unless you have raised money or something.
Um, your burned runway, I've mentioned this a few times,
that's your cash divided
by your monthly operating expenses, right?
So if you have $300,000
and your monthly opex is a hundred k,
you have three months of burn.
Um, this is extremely important.
Um, most businesses, I I like to say that there's like a,
every individual business owner has their, um,
anxiety runway number, right?
Which is basically what's the number you need to like, not
not lose sleep, um, and have this keep, keep you up at night
and based on your risk tolerance, that number is,
will differ, right?
Me personally, if I have probably three
to four months burn in a company in the bank,
I'm, I don't lose sleep.
Uh, my CFO, if we have under 12 months, he's losing sleep.
Uh, so everyone's a little bit different, figure out what
that number is for you, um,
because actually it is more of a mental health number, uh,
sometimes, um, as a business owner.
Then, uh,
and then operating runway, um, it's a similar way
to show the exact same thing.
Actually, I'm curious just what is the burn runway in terms
of number of months of burn
that everyone is comfortable with?
If, if they're willing to share
Like six months, four to six months?
Mm-hmm. Yeah, that's, that's a solid number.
The opposite can happen too, where you have a company that,
uh, that literally has like two
and a half years of burn in their bank
and, uh, you know, they're, they,
they could be making acquisitions,
they could be doing things with those money
or that money that would, uh,
be growing the business or investing in growth.
Um, in terms of growth rate, uh, to me
a gross profit is, is the most operational
metric most of the time.
Um, the only exception would probably be
be because gross profit can,
can also just affect if you may be in a growth mode
and you may be trying to take market share, uh,
in a business, you may be over investing on the opex
side in order to grow.
Uh, and, and so you can still track gross
profit, um, because of that reason.
When we do profit sharing, um, with leadership teams,
it's almo almost always based on gross profit, not ebitda.
Uh, the only time to really start tracking EBITDA is when
you say explicitly that you, uh, wanna sell the company
and, you know, and that that exit planning event,
maybe three, three plus years away, right?
That's the healthy way to do exit planning is to, is
to think three years out.
Um, but that's really when you wanna start monitoring
ebitda, um, and revenue growth.
So that is like the sexy number
that everyone talks about is actually
the least important to me.
Um, I would only focus on revenue growth.
If you're early stage, um, you're looking to, you know,
seek market share or you have some other form of economic
interest in, in growing in, in a space,
and you don't actually need to be profitable.
Uh, and I would say pre-tax profit would be, you know,
another, another good number to track.
Okay. We talked about what's, uh,
how much money should you have, uh,
before you start investing in growth.
Um, and I would say a minimum of three months,
uh, runway as a buffer before you, you spend anything.
And if you have any volatility or seasonal revenue
or you know, large, uh, customer concentration, uh,
you probably wanna raise that to more like six months.
Uh, I would also say that you should be conservative
with how much you expect a growth initiative to cost.
Uh, in my experience, if you're trying, let's say, you know,
one of the, the common ones would be I want another,
I I wanna make another customer
acquisition channel profitable.
In my experience, that takes three to six months of, of,
of actual spend in that space, plus whatever, you know,
fixed cost goes towards staffing in order to do that.
Um, so, you know, depending on where you are
and what costs are, that could be a, you know, a hundred
to 200 k expense, uh, when,
when you really calculate it.
And because sometimes you think, oh, this is,
I'll test this out for a month.
Uh, and either you don't test it long enough
or you don't test it with a large enough budget
and it's ends up just being burning money
because you never got a good result.
So budget, three plus months of testing with,
uh, enough actual testing to generate, um,
statistically significant, uh, numbers.
So ideally that's multiple customers, you know,
10 plus customers a month from that channel.
Um, at the bottom of that funnel,
uh, the only exception here would be is if, if your, um,
payback period on your acquisition costs are under 30 days,
um, in which case you could probably go ham.
Um, but I would still be careful and make small bets first.
I,
okay, we went over each of these, again, this is more
for your reference later.
So traditional financial management, I was a lot
of time manually making spreadsheets for a finance team, uh,
and then making a lot of presentations manually I,
and then reviewing it as a team, right?
Whether that's through a monthly business review, whether
that's through a budgeting process or strategic planning.
Um, the new world of financial management is
you have AI based business intelligence.
Uh, you make sure
and put in the hygiene to keep that up to date.
That's actually the challenge, right,
that you'll run into is how do I best keep my master prompt
or my business brain up to date?
If you're able to do that, then all
of this other stuff becomes irrelevant
because AI does it for you, right?
You can chat with it about it,
you can have it create custom apps around anything you want,
let alone create spreadsheets for you.
Um, you can start creating workflows, uh,
a lot becomes possible.
Uh, the difference in hygiene,
however, is now I need to keep AI up
to date and how do I best do that?
Okay. We have a few more minutes for q and a.
Are you feeding your LLM or LLMs
or your API with monthly
or weekly financial data from your system?
So the bookkeeper,
Yeah. So what we do
now is we have proactive prompting
that has, uh, so we use Slack.
And so we basically have an agent ask every week,
whoever's in charge of the financial performance management
process, um, what updates have happened
across a whole bunch of different things.
And based on that, it updates the master
prompt in the backend.
And that's how we ensure, at least on a weekly basis
for our purposes, a weekly basis is,
is the right cadence to have up to date.
Um, and so we have that across a few different agents.
So we'll have like A-C-H-R-O agent
that will just ask whoever's in charge
of people in the company, was anyone fired?
Was anyone hired? Was anyone promoted? Was anyone demoted?
Um, were there any performance issues? Right?
And based on that boom, boom, boom,
it updates the master prompt.
Um, on the finance side,
you know, how much cash do you have?
I haven't done it such that it, you know,
QuickBooks is loaded in and it automatically checks it
because I actually like the,
I like the manual reminder piece, uh,
for whoever's in charge of finance to actually be looking
that up and writing it down.
Um, though I could see why someone
might wanna automate further.
Um, and then the third
that we do is usually like the customer
acquisition side, right?
Same thing on a weekly basis.
We want to know, um, what CAC looks like per channel,
and that goes out to the person in charge of
that channel, right?
Um, what our spend was versus target, um, number
of leads, new leads, et cetera.
Um, and then a lot of the, the rest of our processes kind
of updated just through our normal day-to-day interaction.
And it updates the master prompt, uh, directly in,
in which of LLM.
Uh, so we use, uh, Gemini in the backend, um,
just for various reasons.
It's the fastest and it's cheap.
Um, and then obviously if we're,
if we're doing changes in cloud code, that's done
through Opus 4.6, um,
and then we have a way to, we're, we're getting into
advanced territory, which we're gonna
cover in the last session.
Um, but,
but basically, um, as you go deeper in, uh, the,
the challenge, like I said, is
how do I keep my master prompt up to date?
Um, and there are sort of low tech or no tech, low tech
and high tech versions of that, um, depending on your needs,
uh, in our case, we, we go with the high tech version.
So you will
Also tell about you, you will also tell about, um,
how to proceed after the cohort, um,
when using Gemini Enterprise, for instance.
Yep. Yep. Okay.
And yeah, there, there's a, there will be a, a
probably an extra session where we're gonna throw in
as well, uh, a session 13 on, on some of this stuff as well.
Okay. For those. Yeah.
Hayden, just going back to how you have your LLM talking
to, uh, the master prompt on the HR example
that you gave, would it be as granular
as John Smith was terminated?
So you would put that in there
and then at the end of the week or month
or quarter, you would have like an annual review
or you would feed that into everything
that's happening on the people side.
Is it that granular?
It, it is that granular.
Um, but the, the chat is smart enough to basically look up,
okay, where, what,
what do I have recorded about John Smith, right?
Okay. John Smith worked in marketing, uh,
and John Smith reported to, you know, Joe
and had Janice and Tiffany as his reports.
And so he would then go and ask questions about who's
replacing John Smith, what's happening, uh, you know,
what is Tiffany and now reporting up to Joe, uh, how,
how do we will actually ask like, how do I consolidate
the things that are missing because John was responsible
for this process, he was responsible
for these people, right?
Um, and what it ends up doing is based on your answers back
and forth, it then goes back
and updates the appropriate knowledge documents in the
master prompt so that anytime anybody in the future,
you know, says something, uh, about John Smith's process
or, um, you know, the RACI involved with the process
that he was in it now knows, okay, actually Tiffany does
that now, or Joe does that now.
Um, you're muted by the way. You
Have a applicant tracking system on your recruitment side
that feeds all the stuff into your master prompt.
And basically all these other disparate systems
that you've used in the past historically are now funneling
into this main master prompt.
Everything funnels into the master prompt.
Um, I, I would like that applicant tracking system.
I have not made it yet, but, uh,
I don't do much hiring anymore.
Thank you.
It's really mind boggling just how, how, uh,
large this whole AI solution can be when you think
of all the pieces of a day-to-day operation.
Yep. Yeah. My approach has been the goal is
to, to build business intelligence.
Um, so when we trained our teams,
the leadership teams often went
through a very similar program to what you're going through.
And then what we realized is the next challenge
after that is getting team buy-in
and actually getting process ownership
and AI comfort with the team.
And so our next step was then training the team on a
similar-ish program that's a little bit deeper, um,
and narrower, uh, in order for the team to then have,
I think I mentioned this last o office hours
to build up role master prompts, right?
So what is Montgomery's, uh, master prompt as opposed
to the company master prompt
and what processes is he involved in
and what decisions does he make and who reports to him
and what meetings is he in, right?
And what's the cadence and the agenda of those meetings.
Um, and then once everyone in the company has done that,
we create what's called a clarity board.
Um, but once everyone in the company has done that,
that then kicks off a process to kind of consolidate all
that information, update the master prompt,
and then pretty much everything is up to date.
And the beauty of that is now it's not your job
to keep the system up to date, right?
Because otherwise you end up becoming, if you go top down,
um, my experience is you end up becoming the bottleneck, um,
for any AI solution.
Um, that's what I did at first,
and then everything just kind
of paused while I was doing too many things.
So I, I think that's, in my opinion,
that's the path going forward if you want
to get like full business intelligence is you need
to go from, you know,
the bottom up from a hierarchy perspective.
Like whoever's closest to the work, uh,
should be the ones owning the processes going forward.
Uh, so that's the approach we've taken.
And just switching gears back to stage three,
is it your goal to introduce that as a product in the market
or just within the empower, uh, community?
What's the long term play there?
Uh, it is our way to support
the business intelligence piece of this.
Um, so I, I look at it as middleware, uh,
between, in, in order to keep your master prompt
and your process up to date
and shareable with your team, which is a real challenge,
like that was the, the challenge I face is a challenge
that pretty much everyone previous cohorts faced.
Um, and so what I, I don't wanna like compete with,
you know, chat GT or clot or anything.
Um, but I do want to teach people how to use the best
product for like workflow solutions.
And then, and then the question is how do you get something
to act as middleware to then keep that updated with
what everyone else is using?
So as an example, on on Friday I did a cloud code training
for two of my companies, um, like a three hour, like, here's
how you install cloud code, here's how,
and everyone knows about, they've all gone through
what you've gone through, but the next level is like, okay,
let's figure out who the actual AI
operators in the company will be.
Um, teach them cloud code
and then tie cloud code into stage three so
that someone can make the updates in cloud code.
And it's then represented as well in stage three.
So that, that's where we're at now.
Um, and maybe another solution comes in
that's better than cloud code,
I'm sure there will be, right?
Um, and the idea is, again, you still need that sort
of business intelligence middleware
to keep everything up to date.
So that's the plan
As this group continues along
and we choose whether it's Notion or Google or stage three,
before I kind of go all in on something, I'm just trying
to understand what's the long-term objective of stage three?
Can we use it? Will, will it be a subscription based?
Is it free to the cohort? That's where my head is.
Yeah. I, it it's free to the cohort for,
uh, a period of time.
Uh, I don't know. I haven't really thought through a lot.
My, my thought was it's likely gonna be tied into a teams
offering that we'll do in the future.
Um, so I'm running a couple teams cohorts right now as a,
as initial betas.
Um, it's also inspiration, I think for you,
you, you can make your own right.
Like I said, it's not, it's not difficult to do.
Um, it's difficult to create something that then, you know,
distributes widely across the customer base.
But even creating your own is, is something
that's not too difficult to do.
Um, I'm certainly not looking for, yeah, for it
to be like a, our, our main revenue generator.
Got it. I think it's great.
And when you say it's not difficult to do,
I'm still having a hard time just keeping up
with the course curriculum,
let alone building out my own thing.
So we'll, we'll take your intelligence, uh, any day over
what I could do myself self.
Um, the, the, the other piece,
uh, to look into, 'cause you mentioned notion
and Google Docs and stuff, um, would be skills.
So, so putting some things into Claude's skills, uh,
and I know there's some people in the alumni
that have done that.
Um, it, it's another, another way
to approach the same problem.
Um, just keep in mind that the large challenge
that you need to face with whatever solution will likely be
keeping everything up to date,
because if it doesn't stay up to date, may, maybe even some
of the beta cohort people here can, can resonate with that,
that, you know, maybe their master prompt is six months old
now, or five months old since they
went through the program in June.
And, uh, it's less useful or,
or they've had to put a lot of effort into like copying
and pasting things to keep it up to date.
Thank you. Yep.
Okay. I think, uh, okay, in the interest of time,
we'll move onto, uh, the work
for this week.
So the good news is, uh, there are five things here.
Uh, three of them are optional.
Uh, but what we, what we would like is for folks to run
through the five steps or exercises
between now and next Monday.
Uh, we're gonna be, uh,
looking at doing a financial health diagnostic, uh,
and also, uh,
we're doing a financial performance, uh, assessment.
Uh, the idea here is that at the end of this conversation,
you're gonna have some financial clarity.
Uh, you'll understand your profitability drivers, uh,
and you'll have, uh, an improved, uh, road roadmap with, um,
your top three opportunities, uh, ranked by impact, um,
the Hayden.
Do you wanna speak a bit about, um,
what makes things optional versus not
and when folks should be, uh, trying to get to those?
The optional here is actually,
so the fractional CFOI highly recommend you try it out.
It can take five minutes if you want.
Um, it's not a complicated prompt.
Um, you just do it after you do the other three, uh,
and it now has the, the context necessary.
And here you can do whatever you want with it, right?
Um, the interactive artifact, if you use spreadsheets
regularly, um,
I highly recommend you do this, uh, simply
because it will save you an immense amount
of time going forward, um, making spreadsheets.
If you never make spreadsheets, uh, maybe you send it
to someone in your company who does, um,
in order to save them time.
But I used to spend, um, probably 10 hours a week
making spreadsheets from scratch.
Um, and I, I, I'd say over the last, since
Claude has been able to get like a decent spreadsheet skill,
um, I have not made a spreadsheet from scratch once
that's been about four months.
So yeah,
if you spend any time making these spreadsheets, I'd check it out.
And so also, uh, access to basic financial records.
So p and l revenue, data
and pricing info will be necessary in order to run these,
uh, these exercises as well.
Uh, we have office hours coming up on Wednesday
at 10:00 AM Pacific time, 1:00 PM Eastern Time.
And then our next session is section session seven, offering
and sales excellence.
And, uh, oh, that doesn't have the right date on it.
It will be on, uh, Monday, the 16th of February.
And that slide will be up. Good for that.
It was great to see everyone today.
Thank you so much, and we'll see you all in circle.
Thank you. Hey, you. Bye-bye. Thanks everyone. Thanks.
Take care. Bye bye.
Session Friday, right? No session Friday.
Nice to see you, Nancy.